chapter 7 the chapel in the same New Bedford there stands a
whaleman's chapel, and few are the moody fishermen shortly bound for the Indian
Ocean or Pacific, who fail to make a Sunday visit to the spot. I am sure that
I did not. Returning from my first morning stroll, I again sied out upon
this special errand. The sky had changed from clear, sunny, cold to driving sleet
and mist. Wrapping myself in my shaggy jacket of the cloth called bare skin, I
fought my way against the stubborn storm. Entering, I found a small,
scattered congregation of sailors and sailors wives and widows. A muffled
silence reigned, only broken at times by the shrieks of the storm. Each silent
worshipper seemed purposely sitting apart from the other, as if each silent
grief were insular and incommunicable.
The chaplain had not yet arrived, and there these silent islands of men and
women sat steadfastly eyeing several marble tablets with black borders
masoned into the walls on either side of the pullpit. Three of them ran something
like the following, but I do not pretend to quote.
sacred to the memory of John Talbot, who at the age of 18 was lost overboard near
the aisle of desolation off Patagonia, November 1st, 1836.
This tablet is erected to his memory by his sister.
Sacred to the memory of Robert Long, Willis Ellery, Nathan Coleman, Walter
Canny, Seth Macy, and Samuel Gl forming one of the boats crews of the ship
Eliza, who were towed out of sight by a whale on the offshore ground in the
Pacific, December 31st, 1839.
This marble is here placed by their surviving shipmates,
sacred to the memory of the late captain Ezekiel Hardy, who in the boughs of his
boat was killed by a sperm whale on the coast of Japan August 3rd, 1833.
This tablet is erected to his memory by his widow.
Shaking off the sleet from my iced glazed hat and jacket, I seated myself
near the door, and turning sideways was surprised to see Quiquake near me.
Affected by the somnity of the scene, there was a wondering gaze of incredulous curiosity in his
countenance. This savage was the only person present who seemed to notice my
entrance, because he was the only one who could not read, and therefore was
not reading those frigid inscriptions on the wall. Whether any of the relatives
of the seaman whose names appeared there were now among the congregation, I knew
not, but so many or the unrecorded accidents in the fishery, and so plainly
did several women present where the countenance, if not the trappings of
some unceasing grief, that I feel sure that here before me were assembled those
in whose unhealing hearts the sight of those bleak tablets sympathetically
cause the old wounds to bleed aresh.
Oh ye whose dead lie buried beneath the green grass, who standing among flowers
can say, "Here, here lies my beloved, you know not the desolation that broods
in bosoms like these. What bitter blanks in those black bordered marbles which
cover no ashes. What despair in those immovable inscriptions? What deadly
voids and unbidden infidelities in the lines that seem to gnaw upon all faith
and refuse resurrections to the beings who have placelessly perished without a
grave? As well might those tablets stand in the cave of elephant as here?
In what census of living creatures the dead of mankind are included? Why it is
that a universal proverb says of them that they tell no tales, though
containing more secrets than the good one sands, how it is that to his name,
who yesterday departed for the other world, we prefix so significant and
infidel a word, and yet do not thus entitle him, if he but embarks for the
remotest indies of this living earth, why the life insurance companies pay
death forfeitures upon immortals, in what eternal unirring paralysis and
deadly hopeless trance yet lies antique Adam who died 60 round centuries ago.
How it is that we still refuse to be comforted for those who we nevertheless
maintain are dwelling in unspeakable bliss. Why all the living so strive to
hush all the dead. Wherefore but the rumor of a knocking in a tomb will
terrify a whole city. All these things are not without their meanings.
But faith, like a jackal, feeds among the tombs, and even from these dead
doubts she gathers her most vital hope.
It needs scarcely be told with what feelings on the eve of a Nantucket
voyage I regarded those marble tablets, and by the murky light of that darkened,
doeful day, read the fate of the whalemen who had gone before me. Yes,
Ishmael, the same fate may be thine. But somehow I grew merry again. Delightful
inducements to embark. Fine chance for promotion, it seems. I, a stove boat,
will make me an immortal by brevitt.
Yes, there is death in this business of whailing, a speechlessly quick, chaotic
bundling of a man into eternity. But what then? Me thinks we have hugely
mistaken this matter of life and death.
Mei thinks that what they call my shadow here on earth is my true substance. Me
thinks that in looking at things spiritual we are too much like oysters
observing the sun through the water and thinking that thick water the thinnest
of air. Me thinks my body is but the leaves of my better being. In fact take
my body who will take it. I say it is not me. And therefore, three cheers for
Nantucket, and come a stove boat and stove body when they will, for stave my
soul. Jove himself cannot.